IVAN MOROZOV | Curriculum Vitae

SUMMARY_

Accelerator physicist at Budker INP and SKIF. My main research interests are nonlinear dynamics, nonlinear integrable systems, symplectic integrators, chaos detection methods, global optimization, dynamic aperture optimization, online optimization, measurements and correction of accelerator optics, applications of ML methods in accelerators, anomaly detection, surrogate models, ML based correction, differentiable modeling.



EDUCATION __

Jul. 2010 BS in Physics, **Novosibirsk State Technical University**, Novosibirsk, Russia Thesis: "Slow beam extraction from synchrotron" | Advisor: Dr. Alexey Petrenko GPA: 4.28/5.00

Jul. 2013 MS in Physics, **Novosibirsk State Technical University**, Novosibirsk, Russia Thesis: "Modeling of nonlinear accelerator elements" | Advisor: Dr. Alexey Petrenko GPA: 5.00/5.00

Additional education _____

2011 Beam Physics with Intense Space Charge, USPAS, Stony Brook University, USA

2012 Accelerator Physics, USPAS, University of Texas at Austin, USA

2012 Accelerator Physics, IASCL, Raja Ramanna Center for Advanced Technology, India

2018 Numerical Methods for Analysis, Design and Modelling, CAS, Greece

2021 Optimization and Machine Learning for Accelerators, USPAS, (online)

2022 Beam Measurements and Diagnostics on an Electron Storage Ring, USPAS, (online)

Work experience _____

Sep. 2008 – Jul. 2017 Research assistant at Budker INP, Russia

- Conducted beam slow extraction simulations for Proton Beam Therapy synchrotron.
- Designed and implemented tools for modeling nonstandard nonlinear accelerator elements, including hollow electron lens collimator and polar integrable lenses.
- Participated in integrable ring modeling based on lens integrable in polar coordinates.
- Developed software for analytical computations of normal forms and control term (Hamiltonian control theory).
- Developed tools for application of Magnus expansion to factorization of accelerator elements into product of Lie exponents.
- Investigated beam-beam compensation by introduction of another IP.

Jul. 2010 - Aug. 2010 Summer Intern (PARTI) at Fermilab, USA

- Contributed to the development and analysis of high-pressure RF cavities for muon accelerator applications.
- Investigated the impact of alignment imperfections on the performance of high-pressure RF cavities.

Feb. 2011 - Feb. 2012 Guest Scientist at Fermilab, USA

- Developed models of hollow electron lens collimator that accounted for hollow beam imperfections: varying radial beam profile and azimuthal harmonics.
- Conducted collimation simulations for the Tevatron using LifeTrack software.

Jun. 2017 - Jun. 2021 Junior researcher at Budker INP, Russia

- Participated in the NICA collider dynamic aperture studies: impact of final focus quadrupole fringe fields
- Developed software for beam dynamics simulations: dynamic Fortran code generation in Wolfram Mathematica with explicit dynamics of derivatives.
- Developed software for chaos detection: decomposition and analysis of trajectories and chaos indicators.
- Perform FMA studies for BINP CTAU collider project.
- Investigated dynamic aperture optimization by fitting coefficient of nonlinear rotation using NSGA-II.
- Applied machine learning methods for anomaly detection in TbT signals and developed advanced processing techniques for TbT data.
- Developed software for frequency and uncoupled Twiss parameters computation from TbT data along with other related functionality.
- Implemented uncoupled Twiss parameters measurement techniques (from amplitude and phase using multiple triplets) at the VEPP-4M collider.
- Served as an accelerator operator at the BINP.
- Served as a student supervisor.

Jun. 2021 – Current Researcher at Budker INP, Russia

- Developed library for differentiable coupled Twiss parameters computation along with its application examples.
- Developed library for differentiable nonlinear dynamics modeling along with its application examples.
- Implemented RCDS algorithm for online optimization with Bayesian optimization usnig GPyTorch and BoTorch.
- Leading code development for differentiable accelerator modeling and extensive library of examples.
- Participated in SKIF dynamic aperture studies, analyzing the effects of higher-order multipole errors and insertion devices, and performing high-fidelity FMA simulations.
- Developed methods and conducted measurements of coupled Twiss parameters from TbT signals at the VEPP-4M collider.
- Implemented the square matrix method for nonlinear dynamics analysis.
- Serving as an accelerator operator at the BINP.
- Served as a student supervisor.

Jun. 2022 - Current Researcher at SKIF, Russia

- Leading nonlinear dynamics research efforts at SKIF.
- Applied machine learning methods for the localization of linear optics errors.
- Investigating application of chaos indicators for characterization of bifurcation fractals for 2D symplectic mappings.
- Investigating application of ML techniques to chaos identification.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE _

Jun. 2023 – Current Teaching assistant at NSTU, Russia, NSTU Mini Technology Course

Research skills _____

Accelerator modeling and optimization, Symplectic integrators, Nonlinear accelerator elements modeling, Nonlinear dynamics, Dynamical systems and stability, Chaos and stability indicators, Nonlinear integrable accelerators, Dynamic aperture optimization, Coupled Twiss parameters, Optics measurements and correction, Application of ML methods in accelerator physics, Accelerator operation, Differentiable accelerator modeling

COMPUTER SKILLS _____

Intermediate: LATEX, C., Docker, Haskell, Matlab, MADX & PTC, Elegant, COSY-INFINITY,

Numpy, Numba, SciPy, scikit-learn, GPyTorch, BoTorch

Advanced: Linux, Bash/Zsh, Python, Pytorch, Fortran, Wolfram Mathematica

Honors & Awards _____

- Distinguished Performance Award (7th IASCL, 2012)
- 2nd place at Young Scientist Conference (accelerator section, Budker INP, 2016)
- Oustanding+ Performance at Optimization and Machine Learning course (USPAS, 2021)

Additional social profiles _____

- MATHEMATICA & Wolfram Language
- YouTube

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS ____

- I. Morozov and E. Levichev, "Dynamical Aperture Control in Accelerator Lattices With Multipole Potentials", CERN Proceedings, 2017
- G. Baranov and A. Bogomyagkov and I. Morozov, and S. Sinyatkin and E. Levichev, "Lattice optimization of a fourth-generation synchrotron radiation light source in Novosibirsk", Phys. Rev. Accel. Beams, 2021
- I. Morozov and Yu. Maltseva, "Coupled twiss parameters estimation from turn-by-turn data", NIM-A, 2024
- T. Zolkin and S. Nagaitsev and I. Morozov and S. Kladov and Y. K. Kim, "Dynamics of McMillan mappings III. Symmetric map with mixed nonlinearity", arXiv:2410.10380, 2024
- T. Zolkin and S. Nagaitsev and I. Morozov and S. Kladov and Y. K. Kim, "Isochronous and period-doubling diagrams for symplectic maps of the plan", arXiv:2412.05541, 2024